A Guide to the Friends of Nelson Record of the Western and Central Virginia Resistance to the Atlantic Coast Pipeline, 2014-2021
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Friends of Nelson Record of the Western and Central Virginia Resistance to the Atlantic Coast Pipeline, 2014-2021
Library of Virginia
53723
7.3 cubic feet (12 boxes and 3 folders).
Friends of Nelson
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Friends of Nelson, Nelson County.
Historical Information
Friends of Nelson (FON) was formed in June 2014 in response to the plans of Dominion Energy, Inc., to construct a pipeline routed through West Virginia, Virginia, and North Carolina. From 2014 until 2020, the Friends of Nelson and allied organizations used a wide variety of activities and actions to oppose the pipeline. On 5 July 2020, Dominion and Duke Energy cancelled the Atlantic Coast Pipeline project.
Scope and Content
Records, 2014-2021, of the Friends of Nelson, an organization located in Nelson County, Virginia, documenting western and central Virginia resistance to the Atlantic Coast Pipeline (ACP) project planned by Dominion Energy, Inc., and Duke Energy Corporation. Papers include announcements, appendices, articles, brochures, correspondence, court records, graphics, maps, notes, petitions, publications, reports, signs, and other documents. Records of other organizations opposing the ACP are included in the collection.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Dominion, 2014-2018
Series II: Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, 2015-2021
Series III: U.S. Forest Service, 2014-2016
Series IV: Virginia Department of Environmental Quality, 2017-2019
Series V: Augusta County, 2014-2018
Series VI: Buckingham County, 2014-2019
Series VII: Nelson County, 2014-2021
Series VIII: Allegheny-Blue Ridge Alliance (ABRA)
Series IX: Arts and Activism
Series X: Community Groups
Series XI: Easements
Series XII: Economics
Series XIII: Eminent Domain
Series XIV: Environmental Impact
Series XV: Environmental Justice
Series XVI: Events
Series XVII: Historic Resources
Series XVIII: Legal
Series XIX: Letters to Agencies and Officials
Series XX: Man Camps
Series XXI: Maps
Series XXII: News Media
Series XXIII: Other Pipelines
Series XXIV: Photographs
Series XXV: Pipes, Pipe Yards, and Storage Areas
Series XXVI: Safety and Public Health
Series XXVII: Surveys
Series XXVIII: Oversize
Contents List
- Finding Aid (Box 1, Folder 0)
- Dominion 2014-2018 (Box 1)
  In late May 2014, landowners in western and central Virignia received letters from Dominion about a new pipeline. Initially called the Southeast Reliability Project, the proposed Atlantic Coast Pipeline LLC (ACP) was a project of Dominion Energy, Inc., and Duke Energy, Corporation. The ACP was a proposed 48 inch, 1400 psi pipeline intended to bring fracked natural gas from the Marcellus Shale Fields in West Virginia through West Virginia, then southeast into Virginia (including Highland, Bath, Augusta, Nelson, and Buckingham Counties) into North Carolina, to an originally planned terminus near Lumberton, NC. After delays brought about by intense opposition to the ACP and by its ballooning cost, Dominion and Duke announced cancellation of the proposed project on 5 July 2020.
  - Dominion mailings, 2014-2018 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Dominion by citizens and groups, 2014-2015, 2018 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Federal Energy Regulatory Commission 2015-2021 (Box 1-2)
  The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission (FERC) is an independent federal agency that regulates the interstate transmission of natural gas, oil, and electricity. FERC also regulates natural gas and hydropower projects, issues documents and rulings related to projects under consideration, as well as requesting information from the proposers. Beginning in 2014, FERC held several hearings on the Atlantic Coast Pipeline. FERC also solicited written comments by citizens and groups on the initial docket number PF15-6, and then on the permanent docket number CP15-554.
  - FERC mailings, 2015-2021 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - FERC Draft Environmental Impact Statement (cd), December 2016 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - FERC Final Environmental Impact Statement (cd), July 2017 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - FERC scoping meeting comments, March 2015, May 2016, February 2017 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Friends of Nelson presentation to FERC, 15 December 2014 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Individual and group submissions to FERC, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Individual and group submissions to FERC, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Individual and group submissions to FERC, 2016-2021 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Individual and group submissions to FERC, no date (Box 2, Folder 2)
- U.S. Forestry Service 2014-2016 (Box 2)
  This series contains documents about the Atlantic Coast Pipeline (ACP) rout the the U.S. Forest Service's George Washington and Monongahela National Forests, as well as the effects of the ACP on sensitive resources in the National Forests.
  - Pipeline route through the George Washington National Forest and the Monongahela National Forest, correspondence, 2014-2016 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Virginia Department of Environmental Quality 2017-2019 (Box 2)
  The Virginia Department of Environmental Quality oversees both the Water Control Board and the Air Pollution Control Board, both of which held hearing and discussions on state permits required by the Atlantic Coast Pipeline.
  - State Air Pollution Control Board papers, 2018-2019 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - State Air Pollution Control Board letters, 2017-2018 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - State Air Pollution Control Board letters, 2019 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - State Water Control Board papers, 2017-2018 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Augusta County, 2014-2018 (Box 2)
  This series includes materials on resistance to the pipeline in Augusta County, gathered primarily by Nancy Sorrells of the Augusta County Alliance.
  - Augusta County Alliance 2014-2018, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Augusta County Alliance papers, 2014-2018 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Augusta County Alliance public relations and outreach (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Augusta County Farm Bureau 2018, 1 folder (Box 2)
    - Augusta County Farm Bureau resolution, 2018 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Buckingham County, 2014-2019 (Box 2)
  This series includes materials on resistance to the pipeline in Buckingham County.
  - Buckingham County Board of Supervisors 2014-2015, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Buckingham County Board of Supervisors papers, 2014-2015 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Petitions to the Buckingham County Board of Supervisors, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Friends of Buckingham 2014-2019, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Papers, 2014-2019 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Press releases, 2015-2018 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Compressor station papers, 2014-2017 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Nelson County, 2014-2022 (Box 3)
  This series includes materials on resistance to the pipeline in Nelson County, primarily the Friends of Nelson.
  - Nelson County official documents, 2014-2021 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Friends of Nelson 2014-2022, 19 folders (Box 3)
    - Anti-pipeline meeting video, 8 June 2014 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Early organizing, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Financial processes, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - A Pipeline Fighters' Guide, by Ron Enders, October 2022 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Mailings, 2014-2016 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Surveys, August 2015 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Press releases, 12 August 2014-3 July 2015 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Public relations and outreach tabling materials--general (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Public relations and outreach tabling materials--economics (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Public relations and outreach tabling materials--property rights (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Public relations and outreach tabling materials--letter writing, 2014-2016 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Public relations and outreach tabling materials--letters, petitions, 2017-2019 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Public relations and outreach tabling materials--elected officials contact sheet (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Public relations and outreach tabling materials--sample membership forms (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Public relations and outreach tabling materials--bumper stickers and brochure (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Public relations and outreach tabling materials--flyers, graphics (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Public relations and outreach--Atlantic Coast Pipeline impacts on Nelson County, updated presentations, 2014-2015 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - 10 Reasons to Oppose the Atlantic Coast Pipeline, reports (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 10 Reasons to Oppose the Atlantic Coast Pipeline (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Allegheny-Blue Ridge Alliance (ABRA), 2014-2022 (Box 3)
  Allegheny-Blue Ridge Alliance (ABRA), formed in response to the proposed Atlantic Coast Pipeline, is a coalition of conservation organizations dedicated to promoting and protecting the environmental integrity of the Allegheny-Blue Ridge region, which encompasses the Central Appalachian Highlands area of Virginia and West Virginia. The formation of ABRA was announced in a press release on 8 September 2014.
  - General papers (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Dominion Pipeline Monitoring Coalition/Pipeline Compliance Surveillance Initiative (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Arts and Activism (Box 3)
  Numerous artists and musicians contributed their talents to the fight against the Atlantic Coast Pipeline. This series includes samples of work by some of the artists.
  - Arts and activism--songs, poems, artwork, and other papers (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Community groups, 2013-2018 (Box 4-5)
  This series includes documents from groups and organizations that, in various ways and at various times, both formally and informally, participated in the fight against the Atlantic Coast Pipeline, including one folder of miscellaneous materials and publications from other organizations. This is by no means a complete listing, nor is the material included here a complete set of materials from the entities represented.
  - All Pain, No Gain (Wintergreen, Va.--Nelson and Augusta Counties), 2014-2015 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Direct Action, 2013-2018 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Dutch Creek and Harris Cove (Nelson County, Va.), 2014 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Dutch Creek and Harris Cove (Nelson County, Va.)--landowner organizing, 2015-2017 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Friends of Horizon--The Appalachian Trail South Alternate Route: Impact on Horizons Village, 26 March 2015 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Friends of Wintergreen (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Pipeline Coordination Committee, 25 May 2015 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Pipeline Education Group (PEG), 20 folders (Box 4-5)
    - Tabling materials (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Tabling materials--route maps (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Tabling materials--eminent domain (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Tabling materials--pipeline failures (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Tabling materials--flooding (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Tabling materials--compressor stations (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Tabling materials--jobs (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Tabling materials--water (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Tabling materials--trucks and traffic (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Tabling materials--social costs (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Tabling materials--fracking--general (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Tabling materials--fracking--health effects (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Tabling materials--fracking--chemicals (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Tabling materials--fracking--water pollution (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Tabling materials--fracking--air pollution (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Tabling materials--fracking--soil contamination (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Tabling materials--fracking--noise and light pollution (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Tabling materials--fracking--earthquakes (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Tabling materials--fracking--alternative energy (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Tabling materials--fracking--politics (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Rockfish Valley Foundation (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Wild Virginia (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Materials and publications from other groups (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Easements, 2014-2021 (Box 5)
  Theis series includes general material on easements, including pointers for landowners considering easement terms and agreements, signed easement agreements, lists of easement agreements copied at the Augusta County Courthouse, and correspondence on easements. Also see the Eminent Domain series below.
  - Augusta County, 2019-2021 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Buckingham County, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Outdoors Foundation, 2014-2017 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Economics, 2015-2016 (Box 5)
  This series includes summaries and reports regarding the economic costs and impact of the Atlantic Coast Pipeline.
  - Economics of the Atlantic Coast Pipeline Considered by Doug Hornig, May 2015 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Are the Atlantic Coast Pipeline and the Mountain Valley Pipeline Necessary? Synapese Energy Economics report, 12 September 2016 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Overview of Economic Impacts of the ACP on Nelson County, remarks by Connie Brennan, 12 September 2016 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Atlantic Coast Pipeline: Executive Summary, by Thomas Hadwin, Friends of Central Shenandoah Valley, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Eminent Domain, 2014-2015 (Box 5)
  Natural gase companies seeking to build a pipeline in the United States must apply for a certificate of public convenience and necessity from the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. If landowners will not sign easements, the certificate allows the company to assert eminent domain in court. File includes materials from eminent domain lawyers. See the Easement series above.
  - Materials from eminent domain lawyers, 2014-2015 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Environmental Impact, 2014-2020 (Box 5)
  This series includes materials related to the various citizen, group, and agency efforts to demonstrate the environmental impacts and damages that the Atlantic Coast Pipeline would cause. It includes things specific to individual counties, e.g. the floodplain zoning ordincance in Nelson County, the well study in Buckingham County, karst in Augusta County. See also the Pipeline Education Group tabling materials in the Community Groups series, tabling materials in the Nelson County Series-Friends of Nelson subseries, and the Oversize series for posters used in tabling.
  - Agricultural and forestal, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Endangered and sensitive species, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Flooding and Floodplains, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Nelson County floodplain ordinance, 2015-2020 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Floodplain maps--Nelson County (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Geohazards, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Karst, caves, and sinkholes, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Landslides, 2015-2016 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Water, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Buckingham County baseline water testing (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Nelson County--Peavine Mountain area (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Nelson County water body crossings--Dutch Creek, Wheeler's Cove, Peavine, 2016-2018 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Nelson County testing (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Environmental Justice, 2015-2018 (Box 6)
  Dominion's siting of a compressor station in Union Hill (Buckingham County, Va.), which is a majority African American community, immediately met resistance as a matter of environmental justice. This series includes both Dominion documents and local research to counter Dominion claims.
  - Environmental justice papers, 2018 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Union Hill (Buckingham County, Va.) Community Development Corporation, 2015-2016 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Events, 2018-2021 (Box 6)
  Numerous meetings, protests, educational events, concerts, training sessions, lobbying events, and other events took place between June 2014 and the July 2021 celebration of the July 2020 cancellation of the Atlantic Coast Pipeline, sponsored by many different individuals and groups.
  - Spruce Creek Camp, 2018 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Moral Call for Ecological Justice, 19 February 2019 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Friends of Nelson celebration, 10 July 2021 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Historic Resources, 2015-2027 (Box 6)
  Section 106 of the National Historic Preservation Act of 1966 (NHPA) requires federal agencies to consider the effects on historic properties of projects they carry out, assist, fund, permit, license, or approve. Thus, as part of its Federal Energy Regulatory Commission (FERC) application process, Dominion was required to survey historic and archaeological resources on the proposed Atlantic Coast Pipeline route. Under the Section 106 process, organiztaions such as historical societies could become consulting parties in order to ensure that cultural resources, including historical structures and archaeological resources were properly surveyed and protected. Surveys often required mitigation efforts, and consulting parties could review and request revision of plans and documents related to the mitigation process. Because FERC did not follow Section 106 requirements, it was two years before the Augusta and Nelson historical societies were abl to get their respective Boards of Supervisors to request and get consulting party status. Included here are materials on historic, archaeological, and cultural resources relevant to locales in the region.
  - Phase I: Historic Architectural Survey of the Atlantic Coast Pipeline Project draft and related papers, July 2017 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Native American sites (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Nelson County Historical Resources, 11 folders (Box 6)
    - African American slave cemeteries (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Cultural attachment--background materials, 2016-2017 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Cultural attachment--correspondence, 2015-2017 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Cultural attachment--Craig County materials, 1995-2016 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Cultural attachment--FERC Resource Report excerpts, 2015 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Cultural attachment--press coverage, 2015-2016 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Norwood-Wingina historic sites--background materials (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Norwood-Wingina historic sites--Survey of Architectural Resources Norwood and Wingina Vicinities Nelson County, June 2014 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Norwood-Wingina historic sites--correspondence, 2014-2015 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Norwood-Wingina historic sites--Rock Cliff, 2015 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Warminster Historic District (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Legal, 2014-2017 (Box 7-8)
  This series includes legal filings, briefs, and other documents opposing the Atlantic Coast Pipelin, as well as commentary on legal matters.
  - Additional Case Documents, 27 folders (Box 7-8)
    - Barr petition for appeal, 8 May 2017 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Barr brief in opposition to respondent, 30 May 2017 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Barr writ certificate (appeal granted without argument), 12 September 2017 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Barr joint appendix designation, 27 September 2017 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Barr joint appendix (folder 1), 18 October 2017 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Barr joint appendix (folder 2), 18 October 2017 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Barr joint appendix (folder 3), 18 October 2017 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Barr brief of appellants, 23 October 2017 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Barr brief of appellants, 17 November 2017 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Barr reply brief of appellants, 1 December 2017 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Barr Virginia Supreme Court opinion and dissent, 5 July 2018 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Casale, et. al. complaint, 2014 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Chaffins motion to expedite appeal, 15 April 2016 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Chaffins brief in opposition to petition for appeal, 9 May 2016 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Chaffins opening brief of appellants, 23 January 2017 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Chaffins reply brief of appellants, 3 March 2017 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Chaffins Virginia Supreme Court opinion, 13 July 2017 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Klemic, et. al. documents, 2014 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Longobardi petition for appeal, 8 May 2017 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - McQuary filing of memorandum, 2015 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Palmer petition for appeal, 23 April 2016 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Palmer brief in opposition to petition for appeal, 16 May 2016 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Palmer writ certificate (appeal granted), 16 September 2016 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Palmer brief of appellee, 21 November 2016 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Palmer reply brief of appellant, 5 December 2016 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Palmer Virginia Supreme Court opinion, 12 July 2017 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Visceglia, et. al. complaint, 14 July 2014 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Other Legal Materials, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - National Resources and Energy Law Symposium, 21 September 2015 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Articles about surveying cases, 2015-2017 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Letters to Agencies and Officials, 2014-2019 (Box 8)
  This series includes letters on issues related to the pipeline from citizens and groups, sent to various agencies, e.g. U.S. Forest Service, or to elected officials. See also letters from citizens and groups in the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission (FERC) series; the Dominion series; and the Virginia Department of Environmental Quailty series.
  - Letters, 2014-2019 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Letters to Nelson County officials, 2014-2016 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Man Camps, 2017-2018 (Box 8)
  There was concern in communities on and near the pipeline route that if construction started, many local campgrounds would become family-unfriendly man camps. This series includes materials on two campground applications to the Buckingham County Planning Commission.
  - Papers to Buckingham County Planning Commission for campgrounds, 2017-2018 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Maps (Box 8-9)
  The non-Dominion maps of the Atlantic Coast Pipeline route with the logos of the Augusta County Alliance, Shenandoah Valley Network, and the Piedmond Environmental Council (PEC) were created for the Alliance and the Network to show things that the Dominion maps (since removed from the Dominion website) did not include on their maps, including parcel lines.
  - Dominion Atlantic Coast Pipeline (ACP) route overview (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Alternate routes (folder 1 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Alternate routes (folder 2 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Alternative routes--east Nelson County (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Augusta County maps (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Buckingham County maps (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Environmental impact maps (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - George Washington National Forest map (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Highland County map (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Nelson County maps (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Nelson County route map prepared by Joyce Burton (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Nelson County map--steep slopes, prepared by Joyce Burton (Box 9, Folder 9)
- News Media, 2014-2021 (Box 9-10)
  Press coverage on the Atlantic Coast Pipeline (ACP) and the fight against it gathered and donated by various people, collected here in chronological order.
  - Letters to the editor, primarily by Doug Wellman, 2014-2021 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - News articles--pipeline issues across the United States, 2014 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - ACP news articles 2014 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - ACP news articles (folder 1), January-June 2015 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - ACP news articles (folder 2), January-June 2015 (Box 9, Folder 13a)
  - ACP news articles July-December 2015 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - ACP news articles 2016 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - ACP news articles 2017 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - ACP news articles January-June 2018 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - ACP news articles July-December 208 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - ACP news articles 2019 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - ACP news articles 2020 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - ACP news articles 2021 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Other Pipelines, 2015 (Box 11)
  This series contains materials on pipelines other than the Atlantic Coast Pipeline (ACP), retained either because issues and activities were relevant to the ACP or because Dominion often cited them as models of its safe construction and operation practices.
  - Papers, 2015 (Box 11, Folder 1)